<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-GB"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-GB" /><updated>2020-03-06T11:44:55-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Landon Getz</title><subtitle>The thoughts of a queer scientist, advocate, baker, and teacher in no particular order.</subtitle><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><entry><title type="html">Rainbow crosswalk vandalism isn’t just an isolated local event, but a national problem</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/canada/2020/03/05/RainbowCrosswalks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rainbow crosswalk vandalism isn’t just an isolated local event, but a national problem" /><published>2020-03-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/canada/2020/03/05/RainbowCrosswalks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/canada/2020/03/05/RainbowCrosswalks/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a joint blog post by Landon Getz and &lt;a href=&quot;https://labandfield.wordpress.com/2020/03/06/rainbow-crosswalk-vandalism-isnt-just-an-isolated-local-event-but-a-national-problem/&quot;&gt;Alex Bond&lt;/a&gt;, appearing today on both their blogs. If you’re interested in reprinting it, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landongetz.com&quot;&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Grand Falls-Windsor, NL to Burnaby, BC, Pride is celebrated in Canada across the summer months. Towns and cities across the country raise the rainbow flag and celebrate with parades, concerts, and parties. Increasingly, many are following the lead of Sydney, Australia, which painted a giant rainbow crosswalk in 2013 to mark Sydney Mardi Gras. Local councils describe these as great ways to signal the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/new-brunswick/rainbow-crosswalk-woodstock-community-pride-paint-1.4210942&quot;&gt;welcoming and inclusive nature of the town&lt;/a&gt;, and celebrating its diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-dnt=&quot;true&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;New rainbow crosswalk painted white overnight in Gibsons on Sunshine Coast BC Canada. 🏳️‍🌈 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/2rDEsqz1zu&quot;&gt;https://t.co/2rDEsqz1zu&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LEA5yzSeYB&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/LEA5yzSeYB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Duane Burnett (@DuaneBurnett) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DuaneBurnett/status/1150072128202346496?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;July 13, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, not everyone shares that view. Because also from Grand Falls-Windsor to Burnaby, there have been more than 40 incidents of deliberate vandalism of rainbow- or trans-flag-coloured  crosswalks since 2015, with new vandalism occuring on an almost weekly basis. The damage ranges from tire burn-out marks, to paint, to actually trying to dig it up from the road. Further, this damage is often covered by local media, including an interview with someone from the LGBTQ2S+ community describing how disappointed they are, and someone from city council &lt;a href=&quot;cbc.ca/news/canada/ottawa/rainbow-crosswalk-vandalism-charge-prescott-1.5214606&quot;&gt;expressing surprise&lt;/a&gt; that someone in their town could do such a thing and vowing to have it repaired. That’s usually where the story ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/d/embed?mid=1XcM6zVqhkgXKqOuKJv7N8BQd3h5iAjKc&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;460px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that defacing rainbow crosswalks is quite obviously a nation-wide problem. Vandalism has been reported in 7 provinces (none that we could find in PEI, Quebec, or Manitoba), in big cities like Toronto and Vancouver, and small towns like Eastern Passage, NS and Coldstream, BC. In some places, there’s repeated vandalism following repairs, including a record six times in one summer in Miramichi, NB.The effects are more than a bit of soiled pavement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These events portray a repeated and deliberate attempt to show LGBTQ2S+ people that they are still not welcome, at least not openly, in these communities. Although city councils are aiming to show LGBTQ+ folks that they are welcome and supported, vandalism of these crosswalks shows that members of these communities, nationwide, do not always agree. And although it is a minority, it’s a sizeable one, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vancouverisawesome.com/events-and-entertainment/intolerance-sexual-identity-canada-1944992&quot;&gt;1 in 4 Canadians&lt;/a&gt; opposed to same-sex marriage 14 years after it became the law of the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is further reflected in the repeated criticisms of rainbow crosswalks in commentaries from religious groups, so-called “concerned” citizens, and others. This opposition sometimes takes the form of direct frustration with LGBTQ2S+ people and their “sins”, and sometimes takes a shot at the use of taxpayer dollars for “ideological” symbols, even though many rainbow crosswalks are paid for by &lt;a href=&quot;https://lacombeonline.com/local/rainbow-crosswalks-unveiled-in-downtown-red-deer-for-third-year&quot;&gt;private organizations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vandalism and vocal criticism tell and show LGBTQ2S+ folks that they still need to be careful where and when they embrace and openly share their identities, and that they still need to “code switch”, changing the way they behave or talk based on who else is around. This burden, of constantly being aware and choosing when to express oneself, is a tiresome effort and one that is not always available to the more visible among the LGBTQ2S+ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In media stories covering these acts of vandalism, they are portrayed as being one-off, isolated, local incidents. In reality, though, it’s a much bigger, nation-wide problem. However, acknowledging that the surrounding community has Queer-supportive folk, and ensuring visible allyship in many forms (including rainbow crosswalks) can go a long way in pushing back against these acts of vandalism. Collectively, the message vandalism to these symbols sends is that we still have a long way to go,and a lot of work to do, before LGBTQ2S+ folk are not just tolerated, not just accepted, but included in Canadian society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">The reality is that defacing rainbow crosswalks is quite obviously a nation-wide problem.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/rainbowcrosswalk.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/rainbowcrosswalk.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating LGBTQ+ Inclusive Classrooms for Equitable Active Learning</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/teaching%20&%20learning/2019/05/05/DCUTLTalk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating LGBTQ+ Inclusive Classrooms for Equitable Active Learning" /><published>2019-05-05T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2019-05-05T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/teaching%20&amp;%20learning/2019/05/05/DCUTLTalk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/teaching%20&amp;%20learning/2019/05/05/DCUTLTalk/">&lt;p&gt;For the educators in the room, have you ever had undergraduate classes that refuse to engage with your course content? I’ve been thinking a lot about those students, and wondering how we can change our teaching to help them engage more actively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, I attended the Dalhousie Conference on University Teaching and Learning. This is the largest conference in Canada that deals with University teaching and learning and had over 150 participants and 52 presentations (unfortunately with too many concurrent sessions for me to see everything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;FYI - a few stats for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dcutl19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dcutl19&lt;/a&gt; - 52 presentations (including two plenaries), by 108 authors, with almost 180 participants including over 20 students.  Thanks to all for being here!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Brad Wuetherick (@bwuetherick) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bwuetherick/status/1123936462188056576?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 2, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference this year was focused on active learning, a project which the centre for learning and teaching at Dalhousie university has working on this past year. Active learning is the process of more actively engaging students in the learning process. This can be done a number of ways, through activities like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adlit.org/strategies/23277/&quot;&gt;Think-Pair-Share&lt;/a&gt;, group exams, group work, clicker questions, group discussion and so on. (As an aside, if you are wondering what a group exam is or how it is administered, I am planning a future blog post on this topic!) These activities are designed to help students be a bit more active in the classroom, rather than just listen to a lecture for which they will lose focus after about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opencolleges.edu.au/informed/features/30-tricks-for-capturing-students-attention/&quot;&gt;10 minutes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of speaking at this conference, but about something a bit more specific. I understand the requirement for active learning in the classroom, and I understand the benefits, but I wondered, “Would I have engaged in the active learning process during my undergrad?” I worried that, especially in my first year, I would have been far too uncomfortable to do so. Let’s back up so I can explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/dcutl19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#dcutl19&lt;/a&gt; listening to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@LandonGetz&lt;/a&gt; speak of his experiences of LGBTQ+ 🏳️‍🌈 inclusivity in STEM classrooms. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/i2sp2fy3ta&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/i2sp2fy3ta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Les TJ (@drlestj) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drlestj/status/1123637049737842689?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 1, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came out to my family as gay in the fall of my first year of University. This came with a period of very personal and emotional stress. Entering into the classroom environment in this state, I felt very uncomfortable and very tense. Because of this, I think I would’ve been very unlikely to participate well in any of the aforementioned active learning activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk at the DCUTL conference was titled “Creating LGBTQ+ Inclusive Spaces for Equitable Active Learning.” My key message was that students who do not feel comfortable in their surroundings are unlikely to participate in the active learning process. I drew on my personal experiences in my first year to explain this discomfort and how an educator might help alleviate that discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary “action items” I asked people to consider including in their classrooms were the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inclusion of Pronouns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My purpose here was to encourage the normalizing of pronoun usage in the classroom. Introducing yourself, as the instructor, with pronouns at the beginning of the semester signals to LGTBQ+ students that you are aware of them and you are a supportive individual. The same is achieved through the inclusion of pronouns in email signatures and in class syllabi. These small actions help non-binary and trans students to identify their pronouns in class without feeling singled out or alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Become a “Visible Ally”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second suggestion is what I’m referring to as “Visible Allyship.” This essentially means that it is not enough to simply &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; an ally, your students also need to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that you are an ally. This can be done through the use of small things like rainbow pins, rainbow flags, and other LGBTQ+ identifying paraphernalia. Importantly, these small objects, when hanging in your office or classroom, signal to LGBTQ+ students that this is a space where they are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been my experience anecdotally. My current PhD supervisor, then honours supervisor, has a “celebrate diversity” pin on his office cork board. When I first met him to discuss doing research, I saw the pin, knew I was in a safe space without having to broach the subject directly. This takes an enormous amount of stress off of the student and made me immediately more comfortable in that environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/CelebrateDiversity.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The very same Celebrate Diversity pin that my supervisor had (has) in his office. (Dal.ca)&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The very same Celebrate Diversity pin that my supervisor had (has) in his office. (Dal.ca)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classroom Code of Conducts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a big one. Much like conferences should always have an explicit code of conduct, which explains what behaviours are not acceptable during the conference, so to should the classroom have a code of conduct. These documents can be short, and signal to students that they have entered into a location where their peers are expected to engage in respectful and courteous ways with you and others within the classroom environment. This can include statements like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We expect all classroom participants to treat each other with dignity and to conduct themselves in a proper and professional manner.”
&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Harassment and sexist, racist, homophobic, or exclusionary jokes will not be tolerated”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These codes of conduct should be made explicit on day one, and be included in the syllabus. It is also a good idea to have a plan for what the students should do if this code of conduct is breached, and make that explicit in your syllabus as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highlight LGBTQ+ Staff, Faculty, and Students (when appropriate).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many LGBTQ+ youth, finding role models is hard. This is especially true in traditionally heterosexual and cis-gendered environments like Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics. For this reason, I think it is incredibly beneficial to students to highlight those in your programs (and beyond) that identify as a member of a minority group. Doing this allows students to find role models, and recongize the folks they can be immediately open with and ask questions (about being LGBTQ+ in STEM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A word of caution. DO NOT highlight LGBTQ+ staff, faculty, or students without express consent from them. It is possible for a staff member to be open with their immediate workplace, but not want their identity on speakerphone to the whole institution (or beyond). Without express consent, it is quite easy to accidentally out a faculty member to their family/friends and this can be EXTREMELY harmful. Just ask before you highlight anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk was designed to offer these suggestions to make the classroom a more equitable place for all to feel comfortable engaging in the active learning process. I hope that some other educators can find these suggestions useful in navigating what can be a complex classroom environment, and make sure that all students feel welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final note: remember that sometimes it’s not what you say, it’s what you don’t say. I believe that most educators are not EXPLICITLY making an unwelcoming environment for students. However, without active signals that the classroom is a welcome place for LGBTQ+ students, they may feel uncomfortable regardless. Be mindful of how environments might feel for diverse students and use these 4 suggestions to more actively make the classroom comfortable for LGBTQ+ students.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">A summary of my presentation at the Dalhousie Conference on University Teaching and Learning on LGBTQ+ Inclusive Spaces. &quot;Quick tips&quot; included!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/classroomdiversity.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/classroomdiversity.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">LGBTSTEMinar 2019</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/2019/01/12/LGBTSTEMinar19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LGBTSTEMinar 2019" /><published>2019-01-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-01-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/2019/01/12/LGBTSTEMinar19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/lgbtq+/stem/2019/01/12/LGBTSTEMinar19/">&lt;p&gt;Header Photo: © Institute of Physics/Piers Macdonald&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was written on the plane home from London, but wasn’t posted until May 5th, 2019.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Helen Pain, from the Royal Soceity of Chemistry, spoke last and closed the LGBTSTEMinar on January 11th, 2019. Some of the keywords she took away from the conference were “joyous,” “laughter,” “safety.” I honestly couldn’t have summed it up better myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I flew overseas, from Canada to the UK, to attend my first LGBTSTEMinar just last week. The LGBTSTEMinar is a Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics conference which centres the voices of LGBTQ+ folks. There were 9 science talks, two keynotes, and a panel discussion, with a major focus on the science being done by the folks presenting. This is the 4th annual event, and has been hosted in Sheffield, York, and this year at the Institute of Physics in London. Like others, whose feelings I surveyed after the event, I have a hard time explaining how incredible the day was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event allowed us to be our complete selves, without concern for our safety, how we might be percieved, and whether attaching our queerness to science will negatively effect our careers. I have never been to a conference quite like it - least of all a conference with as much laughter and joy - and it was incredible, not to mention the quality of the science, which included astrophysics, machine learning, molecular biology, disease ecology, and glaciology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Day 6 in the UK:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;- One of the most profound experiences of my lifetime (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LGBTSTEMinar19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#LGBTSTEMinar19&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thanks for making it such a success everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Landon Getz (@LandonGetz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz/status/1083871950324359168?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today still, regular academic conferences are  not a safe place for LGBTQ+ minorities; moreso for Trans/Non-binary folks than others. Occassionally they might be “technically” safe spaces, but are not inclusive, with the lack of correct pronoun usage and rampant heteronormativity. The LGBTSTEMinar fills a massive gap in current Science meetings. For LGBTQ+ minorities, it allows the celebration of science without the trouble these minorities often experience in largely straight crowds. Further, events like the LGBTSTEMinar allow LGBTQ+ folks in STEM to identify and find their communtiy within STEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I have to say I got a bit choked up when I walked in &amp;amp; saw this massive rainbow 🌈&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It overwhelmed me to walk into a room &amp;amp; feel so immediately validated &amp;amp; completely welcome.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thank you so so so much to everyone involved in all the organisation.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LGBTSTEMinar19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#LGBTSTEMinar19&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/G279kQaZzP&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/G279kQaZzP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Niamh Kavanagh (@NiamhTalking90) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NiamhTalking90/status/1083660239885529088?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intention for travelling overseas for this event was mostly reconnaisance. Atlantic Canada suffers from the same problem, and in my experience does not have a strong LGBT community in STEM. It’s my intention to fix that by bringing a version of the LGBTSTEMinar to the Maritime provinces. I hope that someday events like this might be commonplace, so scientists can celebrate science and queerness together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving London today has me a bit overwhelmed. The folks I met this last week were all incredible and I can’t wait to return to catch up with them at another STEMinar. The LGBTSTEMnar was easily one of the most impactful events i’ve been to in my lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">The LBGTSTEMinar was easily one of the most impactful events I've been to in my (short) lifetime. Photo - © Institute of Physics/Piers Macdonald</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://epi-rsc.rsc-cdn.org/globalassets/07-news-events/rsc-news/news-articles/2019/01-january/5150_lgbtsteminar-networking-3_f2a-1600.jpg?version=67d5f1eb&amp;width=1120&amp;format=jpg&amp;quality=60" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://epi-rsc.rsc-cdn.org/globalassets/07-news-events/rsc-news/news-articles/2019/01-january/5150_lgbtsteminar-networking-3_f2a-1600.jpg?version=67d5f1eb&amp;width=1120&amp;format=jpg&amp;quality=60" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A New Years Eve Reflection</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/reflection/2018/12/31/NewYearsEveReflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A New Years Eve Reflection" /><published>2018-12-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-12-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/reflection/2018/12/31/NewYearsEveReflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/reflection/2018/12/31/NewYearsEveReflection/">&lt;p&gt;Looking back at 2018 gives me a lot to think about. These reflections shine light on some of these thoughts: what went well, what didn’t, how I can do/be better in 2019. Instead of setting hard goals, i’m looking to set themes for 2019. This way, I don’t have to gauge myself on a black and white scale (achieved goal or didn’t achieve goal), but rather can give myself food for thought to answer the above questions again on December 31st, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What Went Well:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was pretty productive as far as work goes. I participated in 3 conferences, published 3 papers (2 first-author) and 4 commentaries at publications including The Conversation, The Halifax Chronicle Herald, The National Post, The Hastings Centre Forum Blog, and Impact Ethics. I was hired as a Part-Time Academic to teach the First-Year Chemistry course at Dalhousie University, and have greatly enjoyed working with that team. A first this year, I was invited onto the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/listen/shows/information-morning-ns&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Information Morning Radio Show&lt;/a&gt; with Host Portia Clark to discuss being LGBTQ in STEM. This followed my twitter thread about LGBTSTEMDay on June 4th, and was an honour!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-cards=&quot;hidden&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Today is the first annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LGBTSTEMDay?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#LGBTSTEMDay&lt;/a&gt;! So, naturally, I need to write a small thread to share my story/feelings/understanding with friends and colleagues...being an &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LGBTQIA?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#LGBTQIA&lt;/a&gt; STEM student isn&amp;#39;t always easy &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/phdchat?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#phdchat&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/JfjRgyU0mi&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/JfjRgyU0mi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Landon Getz (@LandonGetz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz/status/1014864300970840075?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;July 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I participated in 2 Science Communication platforms, Dal Science’s Ask a Scientist Campaign and Halifax’s first Science Slam! These events challenged me personally and professionally and I can’t wait for the #scicomm I do in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also had a pretty successful year in home baking! I succeeded in making croissants for the first time just last week, made Ramen from a book I got for Christmas, perfected some of my sourdough and conventional bread-making techniques, nailed some home-made pizzas (long fermented dough for incredible flavour) and I discovered tea-cakes (i’m obsessed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;display:inline-flex;&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Br_A0dLF-ki/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;12&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:16px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Br_A0dLF-ki/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 19% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;50px&quot; height=&quot;50px&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 60 60&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; xmlns=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;none&quot; stroke-width=&quot;1&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot;&gt;&lt;g transform=&quot;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&quot; fill=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding-top: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&quot;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 12.5% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: auto;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/Br_A0dLF-ki/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Landon Getz (@landgetz)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2018-12-29T20:25:30+00:00&quot;&gt;Dec 29, 2018 at 12:25pm PST&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-permalink=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BgwrTNIAXo3/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;12&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:16px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BgwrTNIAXo3/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 19% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;&quot;&gt;&lt;svg width=&quot;50px&quot; height=&quot;50px&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 60 60&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; xmlns=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink=&quot;https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;&lt;g stroke=&quot;none&quot; stroke-width=&quot;1&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot;&gt;&lt;g transform=&quot;translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)&quot; fill=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&lt;g&gt;&lt;path d=&quot;M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/g&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding-top: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;&quot;&gt; View this post on Instagram&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 12.5% 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: auto;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/BgwrTNIAXo3/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;amp;utm_medium=loading&quot; style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A post shared by Landon Getz (@landgetz)&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2018-03-25T21:02:46+00:00&quot;&gt;Mar 25, 2018 at 2:02pm PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//www.instagram.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;What Didn't&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year brought a few firsts, but the most striking was the loss of my first close family member. I’ve been lucky up until now to not have lost anyone I was close to, but my Grandma Shirley passed away this last spring. Losing family members is hard, and I can say that I wasn’t expecting the “gut-punch” that it would actually be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet tw-align-center&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Here’s my grandmother, recently passed, living her life as a powerful woman with grace and love. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/NvHhzvqdRW&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/NvHhzvqdRW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Landon Getz (@LandonGetz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz/status/971863564867665920?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work-life balance took a bit of a hit this year, with a lot of stress and time put into work. It paid off, in terms of outcomes, but I now understand that this rushed pace makes my actions less considered, and potentiates mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;How Can I Do/Be Better&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s talk themes. My themes for next year include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Slow Movement&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Science Communication and Outreach&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Community Growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. The Slow Movement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slowmovement.com/slow_food.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Slow Movement&lt;/a&gt; started in Food and Agribusiness in Italy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Slow Food movement has its origins in the 1980s in Italy.  When McDonald’s planned to build an franchise outlet near the Piazza di Spagna in Rome in 1986, Carlo Petrini organised a demonstration in which he and his followers brandished bowls of penne as weapons of protest.  Their demonstration was successful and soon after, Carlo founded the International Slow Food Movement which runs counter to the fast food, fast life, non-sustainable food production and the eroding of local economies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, although i’ll admit i’ve only dabbled here slightly, the argument is that moving slower (distinguised from doing less, which is not really the argument) allows people to think, prepare, and act deliberatly. This is done by forging connectedness and rejecting the fast pace of modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, this movement has been explored in a few books &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Slow-Professor-Challenging-Culture-Academy/dp/1487521855/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1546266391&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+slow+professor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Slow Professor: Challenging the Culture of Speed in the Academy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Barbara K. Seeber and Maggie Berg (which I am currently reading!) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0676975739&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;In Praise of Slow : How a Worldwide Movement Is Challenging the Cult of Speed&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Carl Honore (which is on my reading list!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Science Communication and Outreach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t belabour this point. I am hoping to continue to push my comfort zone this year and spread scientific knowledge to the public. It can be hard to do, and i’m only just beginning, but i’m looking forward to continuing this work into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Community Growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will admit, there is one goal at the heart of this theme. I am looking to build an LGBTQ+ STEM event at Dalhousie this year, as a precursor event to a full Atlantic Canadian LGBTQ STEM Conference in 2020. This will involve meeting and learning for a variety of people in my community (and outside it). This, along with continued work at Urban Gardens/Farms around Halifax, I hope to grow my personal community and the communities i’m apart of in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018 had it’s ups and downs, but I definitely appreciate the time I can take to reflect on it. Moving onward into 2019, I hope you can take some time to reflect too. Happy New Years folks!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">Good, Bad, and Next Year.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://c.pxhere.com/images/2e/9b/e212a78faf467af42bf8ad19eebb-1460271.jpg!d" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://c.pxhere.com/images/2e/9b/e212a78faf467af42bf8ad19eebb-1460271.jpg!d" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gay Blood Vs. Gay Sperm Donation - A Disconnect</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/2018/12/02/BloodBanVsSpermDonation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gay Blood Vs. Gay Sperm Donation - A Disconnect" /><published>2018-12-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-12-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/2018/12/02/BloodBanVsSpermDonation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/2018/12/02/BloodBanVsSpermDonation/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve long argued that Canadian Blood Services and Health Canada’s current regulation regarding the Gay Blood Ban is &lt;a href=&quot;https://impactethics.ca/2017/08/24/a-reflection-on-blood-donation-policy-in-canada/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;misguided&lt;/a&gt;. The Liberal Government has failed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://trudeaumetre.polimeter.org/promise/4404&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;promises&lt;/a&gt; to “end” the gay blood ban in Canada, and instead reinforced it by downgrading the ban from 5 years to 1 year. To me, reducing the ban still says that blood coming from Gay men is risky. This is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; the message we got in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health Canada is working on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/programs/consultation-assisted-human-reproduction-regulations/document.html&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;amendments&lt;/a&gt; to the Assisted Human Reproduction Act. These amendements, among others, include changes to the deferment period for gay men sperm donation. There has been a lot of media attention regarding the gay blood ban since 2015, however much less attention has been given to the changes to sperm donation rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reported changes will see a gay men sperm donation &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/drugs-health-products/biologics-radiopharmaceuticals-genetic-therapies/applications-submissions/guidance-documents/semen-special-access-program/technical-requirements-therapeutic-donor-insemination.html#a2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lifetime ban&lt;/a&gt; reduced to a deferment period of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/programs/consultation-assisted-human-reproduction-regulations/technical-directive.html#a2.1.1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;6 months&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;b&gt;2.1.1(l)&lt;/b&gt;) following a sexual encounter with another man. This change is an obvious step in the right direction. But as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailyxtra.com/new-draft-of-assisted-human-reproduction-act-continues-anti-gay-discrimination-127999&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the headline at DailyXTRA reads&lt;/a&gt;, it still “continues anti-gay discrimination”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t help but ask myself where Health Canada came up with the 6-month number. The HIV virus is rarely transmitted via semen in patients with low blood virus counts. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hiv.gov/hiv-basics/hiv-prevention/using-hiv-medication-to-reduce-risk/hiv-treatment-as-prevention&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;if patients are treated and achieve undetectable viral counts in the blood, risk of sexual transmission is practically zero&lt;/a&gt;. Further, &lt;a href=&quot;https://impactethics.ca/2018/10/26/thicker-than-water-slow-movement-on-blood-policy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;as I have argued before&lt;/a&gt;, men who have sex with men are not automatically at higher-risk for HIV infection. However, certain behaviours - such as promiscuous, anonymous, or unprotected sex - can increase your risk of HIV infection regardless of your sexual orientation. Countries in Europe, notably Italy and Spain, have begun screening blood donation patients based on behaviours, rather than a blanket sexual-orientation based ban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; data-footer=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/70626035@N00/15286494053/in/photolist-phPh7i-djmrGq-djmsAz-djmn37-djkV67-5FCC2H-djmtS8-djm5K2-djmnxW-djkTbm-djmxr8-djmwrL-djmtGh-djkSV1-djkRij-4oKH5j-q4PieJ-c6E6eu-24HEjtq-dT9Z9r-pAQYsy-dMJD2i-7HEAKE-d8ZSaC-uuJcY-8JYgqe-Q4nZJX-22LZibZ-TRhNqK-8R2A51-QSKarS-rz1T9Y-6YXq11-hYwimf-87oXPu-23UPR7A-Ew2FTZ-EugVdD-p95fbg-234xKXJ-2kgBcD-sgQ2XZ-6HSP9-rbfCV-pP1aaH-8Dc9XM-qAFq1w-KcqUFT-oGi1bs-cB8un7/&quot; title=&quot;Día Mundial de la Lucha contra el Sida * World AIDS Day&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7573/15286494053_274721f723_o.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1200&quot; height=&quot;798&quot; alt=&quot;Día Mundial de la Lucha contra el Sida * World AIDS Day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 6-month deferment on sperm donation for men doesn’t follow Health Canada’s current policy on the deferment period for gay blood donation (1 year currently), and Health Canada has not (to the best of my knowledge) explained this distinction. Considering Spain and Italy have had no “public-health crisis” as a result of behavioural-based screening, and that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americasblood.org/media/27919/stmnt_060309_deferrals-msm.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Red Cross and American Association of Blood Banks&lt;/a&gt; support this approach, I’m surprised Health Canada is so weary about gay blood and sperm donation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today (December 2nd, 2018) is Health Canada’s day to consult the people of Halifax on the proposed changes to the Assisted Human Reproduction Act. I have the following questions for Health Canada regarding the proposed changes for sperm donation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul style=&quot;padding-left:10px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What evidence do you have that a 6-month ban for sperm donation is appropriate?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Why the disconnect between Health Canada's policy on gay blood donation vs. gay sperm donation?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you intend to rectify this disconnect?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that we can work together to build a world that we will be proud to live in. It is up to the Government of Canada to lead efforts to reduce discrimination towards LGBTQ+ folks in society. To achieve that, we must work towards removing bans and deferment periods based on sexual-orientation blanket bans for &lt;i&gt;both&lt;/i&gt; blood donations and sperm donations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">I've long argued that Canadian Blood Services and Health Canada's current regulation regarding the Gay Blood Ban is misguided. Is Health Canada getting it wrong again with the Assisted Human Reproduction Act?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/images/HIVBlood.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/images/HIVBlood.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why we are not ready for genetically designed babies</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/gene%20editing/ethics/law%20&%20policy/2018/11/27/WhyWeAreNotReadyforGeneticEditedBabies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why we are not ready for genetically designed babies" /><published>2018-11-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-11-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/gene%20editing/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/11/27/WhyWeAreNotReadyforGeneticEditedBabies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/gene%20editing/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/11/27/WhyWeAreNotReadyforGeneticEditedBabies/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/profiles/francoise-baylis-392841&quot;&gt;Françoise Baylis&lt;/a&gt;, Professor and Canada Research Chair in Bioethics and Philosophy, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theconversation.com/institutions/dalhousie-university-1329&quot;&gt;Dalhousie University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/profiles/graham-dellaire-402398&quot;&gt;Graham Dellaire&lt;/a&gt;, Director of Research and Professor of Pathology, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theconversation.com/institutions/dalhousie-university-1329&quot;&gt;Dalhousie University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/profiles/landon-j-getz-521552&quot;&gt;Landon J Getz&lt;/a&gt;, Ph.D. Candidate in Microbiology and Immunology, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theconversation.com/institutions/dalhousie-university-1329&quot;&gt;Dalhousie University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is republished from &lt;a href=&quot;http://theconversation.com&quot;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt; under a Creative Commons license. Read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/why-we-are-not-ready-for-genetically-designed-babies-107756&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The media is buzzing with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/612458/exclusive-chinese-scientists-are-creating-crispr-babies/&quot;&gt;surprise news&lt;/a&gt; that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2018/11/crispr-bombshell-chinese-researcher-claims-have-created-gene-edited-twins&quot;&gt;Chinese researcher, Jainkui He&lt;/a&gt;, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apnews.com/4997bb7aa36c45449b488e19ac83e86d&quot;&gt;created the world’s first genome-edited twins&lt;/a&gt;. He did this, ostensibly, to provide resistance to HIV, the virus that causes AIDS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. He, reportedly working with former Rice University supervisor Michael Deem, capitalized on work in 2012 by Jennifer Doudna and Emmanuel Charpentier, who introduced a new and easier way of altering the DNA of human and non-human organisms using &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/beyond-just-promise-crispr-is-delivering-in-the-lab-today-77596&quot;&gt;CRISPR-Cas9 technology&lt;/a&gt;. He also built upon the work of molecluar biologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.broadinstitute.org/bios/feng-zhang&quot;&gt;Feng Zhang&lt;/a&gt;, who optimized this genome editing system for use in human cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s claim moves human germline genome editing from the lab to the delivery room   — something other scientists might have been thinking about despite &lt;a href=&quot;https://impactethics.ca/2018/11/26/first-crispr-babies-where-are-our-ethics/&quot;&gt;ethical concerns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/th0vnOmFltc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Jainkui He explains why his lab edited the genome of twin baby girls, Nana and Lulu, when they were embryos.&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific community has expressed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-07545-0&quot;&gt;widespread condemnation&lt;/a&gt; of He’s decision to initiate a pregnancy using genetically modified embryos   — as “dangerous, “irresponsible” and “crazy.” What if mistakes are made? How can we be sure this powerful technology will benefit humankind? Are we ready for the consequences of genetically engineering our own evolution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We argue that we cannot allow individual scientists to decide the fate of the human genome. Heritable human genome editing poses a significant existential threat because changes may persist throughout the human population for generations, with unknown risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctvnews.ca/health/you-can-t-pretend-to-be-god-experts-condemn-claimed-gene-editing-of-babies-1.4192563&quot;&gt;commit to inclusive global dialogue&lt;/a&gt;   — involving experts and the public   — to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www8.nationalacademies.org/onpinews/newsitem.aspx?RecordID=12032015a&quot;&gt;develop broad societal consensus on what to do with genetic technologies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Possible mutations or forced sterilization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He announced to the world that he edited the genome of human embryos for seven couples using CRISPR-Cas9 technology. According to He, two of these embryos resulted in a pregnancy, and twin girls (Lulu and Nana, which are pseudonyms) were born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the editing was to confer resistance to HIV by modifying the CCR5 gene (the protein doorway by which HIV enters human cells). He claims that these edits have been verified in both twins and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2018/11/26/claim-of-crispred-baby-girls-stuns-genome-editing-summit/&quot;&gt;this data has been looked over and called “probably accurate&lt;/a&gt;” by George Church, a world-renowned Harvard geneticist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence suggests, however, the procedure was unnecessary, is unlikely to provide benefit and could even cause harm. Although the father of Lulu and Nana was HIV positive, it is unlikely that he would have passed this disease to his children using standard IVF procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The children born of genome editing are genetic mosaics with uncertain resistance to HIV and perhaps decreased resistance to viral diseases like influenza and West Nile. This is because the CCR5 gene that He disabled plays an important role in resistance to these diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well, there is the possibility of unintended mutations caused by the CRISPR procedure. These health risks cannot be overstated, as the repercussions for these twin girls, in terms of their susceptibility to infectious diseases or cancer will likely be a cause for concern throughout their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another uncertain consequence for the twins concerns their reproductive health and freedom. As they approach reproductive age will they face the possibility of “forced” sterilization to prevent their edited genes being passed on to future generations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Multiple investigations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Southern University of Science and Technology in Shenzhen, China, where He is employed (currently on leave from February 2018 to January 2021), has distanced itself from the researcher and will form an independent international committee to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sustc.edu.cn/en/info_focus/2871&quot;&gt;investigate the widely publicized, controversial research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://images.theconversation.com/files/247599/original/file-20181127-76737-nyfwu8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Feng Zhang, center, an institute member of Harvard and MIT’s Broad Institute, reacts to reporters on the issue of world’s first genetically edited babies after the Human Genome Editing Conference in Hong Kong on Nov. 27, 2018. (AP Photo/Vincent Yu)&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Feng Zhang, center, an institute member of Harvard and MIT’s Broad Institute, reacts to reporters on the issue of world’s first genetically edited babies after the Human Genome Editing Conference in Hong Kong on Nov. 27, 2018. (AP Photo/Vincent Yu)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rice University, where Michael Deem is employed, has also said &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2018/11/26/rice-university-opens-investigation-into-researcher-who-worked-on-crisprd-baby-project/&quot;&gt;they will investigate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shenzhen HarMoniCare Women’s and Children’s Hospital launched an inquiry into the validity of the ethics documents provided by He documenting research ethics approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the ethics approval was only uploaded to the Chinese Clinical Trial Database on Nov. 8 as a retrospective registration   — likely around the time that the twins were purportedly born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Designer babies by powerful elites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Genetic Genie out of the bottle, we have to ask whether we need any more time to reflect on the ethics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A just and fair society is one with less disparity and more justice. A predictable consequence of allowing (nay, encouraging) individuals to genetically modify their children will be greater disparity and greater injustice   — and not only because of limited access to genome editing technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of significant concern is the inevitable increase in discrimination, stigmatization and marginalization as powerful scientific and corporate elites decide which traits are desirable and which traits are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although He disavows any interest in so-called “designer babies” whose parents have chosen their children’s eye-colour, hair-colour, IQ and so on, we are forced to contemplate such a “eugenic” dystopian future should we continue down this path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human genome belongs to all of us. As such, we need to commit to the hard work of making good on the 2015 admonition by the Organizing Committee for the International Summit on Human Gene Editing to work towards &lt;a href=&quot;http://www8.nationalacademies.org/onpinews/newsitem.aspx?RecordID=12032015a&quot;&gt;“broad societal consensus”&lt;/a&gt; on how we should proceed with, or not proceed with, editing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this regard it is heartwarming to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/612465/crispr-inventor-feng-zhang-calls-for-moratorium-on-baby-making/&quot;&gt;Feng Zhang&lt;/a&gt; call for a moratorium on implantation of edited embryos and remind his scientific colleagues that “in 2015, the international research community said it would be irresponsible to proceed with any germline editing without ‘broad societal consensus about the appropriateness of the proposed application.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Disclosure statement&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Françoise Baylis has received funding from the Canadian Institute of Health Research and the Canada Research Chairs Program.
Graham Dellaire receives funding from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR).
Landon J Getz receives funding from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation's page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/107756/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&quot; alt=&quot;The Conversation&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!-- End of code. If you don't see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: http://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">Written by Françoise Baylis, Graham Dellaire, and Landon J. Getz, originally published at The Conversation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/GeneEditBabies.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/GeneEditBabies.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Thicker Than Water - Slow Movement on Blood Policy</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&%20policy/2018/10/26/ThickerThanWater/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thicker Than Water - Slow Movement on Blood Policy" /><published>2018-10-26T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/10/26/ThickerThanWater</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/10/26/ThickerThanWater/">&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;a href=&quot;www.impactethics.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Impact Ethics&lt;/a&gt; on October 26th, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/b&gt; provides an update on Canadian Blood Services’ progress in updating outmoded policies on gay blood donation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year Canadian Blood Services, and Health Canada, have made little progress on their blood donation policies for gay men. The Liberal Party of Canada made &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liberal.ca/realchange/ending-msm-blood-donation-ban/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;significant promises&lt;/a&gt; to the LGBTQ+ community in terms of the gay blood ban and have yet to deliver on these promises. As an update to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://impactethics.ca/2017/08/24/a-reflection-on-blood-donation-policy-in-canada/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; here on&lt;em&gt; Impact Ethics&lt;/em&gt;, I will begin by covering a quick history on the blood ban in Canada, move into what changes we have seen on this issue in the past year, and end on what needs to be done to improve the state of Canadian policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, Canadian Blood Services requires a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blood.ca/en/blood/am-i-eligible/about-msm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;one-year sexual abstention period&lt;/a&gt; for gay and bisexual men (men who have sex with other men) prior to donating blood. Importantly, this policy has been updated from the five-year gay blood-ban and the previous lifetime ban. Largely, these policies stem from the AIDS crisis, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news2/background/taintedblood/bloodscandal_timeline.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;the Tainted Blood Scandal&lt;/a&gt; that occurred around the world and in Canada, respectively. The public was worried about contracting HIV from the blood donations of gay men, and Health Canada responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div data-shortcode=&quot;caption&quot; id=&quot;attachment_4287&quot; style=&quot;width: 650px&quot; class=&quot;wp-caption aligncenter&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img data-attachment-id=&quot;4287&quot; data-permalink=&quot;https://impactethics.ca/2018/10/26/thicker-than-water-slow-movement-on-blood-policy/red_blood_cell/&quot; data-orig-file=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=640&amp;#038;h=320&quot; data-orig-size=&quot;1920,960&quot; data-comments-opened=&quot;0&quot; data-image-meta=&quot;{&amp;quot;aperture&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;credit&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;camera&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;created_timestamp&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;focal_length&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;iso&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shutter_speed&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;title&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;orientation&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0&amp;quot;}&quot; data-image-title=&quot;Red_Blood_Cell&quot; data-image-description=&quot;&quot; data-medium-file=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=640&amp;#038;h=320?w=300&quot; data-large-file=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=640&amp;#038;h=320?w=640&quot; class=&quot;size-full wp-image-4287&quot; src=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=640&amp;#038;h=320&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;320&quot; srcset=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=640&amp;amp;h=320 640w, https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=1280&amp;amp;h=640 1280w, https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=150&amp;amp;h=75 150w, https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=300&amp;amp;h=150 300w, https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=768&amp;amp;h=384 768w, https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg?w=1024&amp;amp;h=512 1024w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;wp-caption-text&quot;&gt;Image description: red blood cells&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a bit over two years since Canada moved from the five-year blanket ban to the one-year deferral period. Since that time, many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2018/08/20/blood-donation-appeal-canada-gay-men-ban_a_23502861/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;advocacy groups&lt;/a&gt; and an &lt;a href=&quot;https://petitions.ourcommons.ca/en/Petition/Details?Petition=e-1589&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;E-petition&lt;/a&gt; have argued that the 1-year ban is still not backed by science. Largely, this is because they argue, and I agree, that a blanket ban on gay blood does not accurately reflect who is a “high-risk” HIV donor. Further, this can perpetuate the idea that gay men are sick/carry disease, which leads to further stigmatization and “othering” of this group. Canadian Blood Services has noted that they are reviewing research in order to safely lower the one-year ban to a three-month ban (in line with the current UK policy), and have &lt;a href=&quot;https://blood.ca/en/blood/am-i-eligible/about-msm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;conducted focus groups&lt;/a&gt; in considering a behavioural-based approach to screening. Behavioural-based approaches are those which screen blood donors not on their sexuality, but on the behaviours which put them at risk for HIV infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what the science says. Many of the tests available for HIV detection have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5554671/#cit0013&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;sensitivities and specificities that approach 100%,&lt;/a&gt; meaning that missing a contaminated sample is very unlikely after the window of detection (two-weeks from infection). Further, previous reductions in blood-bans have not resulted in significant increases in blood contamination. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23398193/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;a study in 2013&lt;/a&gt; showed that when the UK changed their policy from a five-year to a one-year deferral in 2011, the number of blood contamination increased only marginally – to one contaminated sample every &lt;em&gt;455 years&lt;/em&gt; – while it made 46% of men who have sex with men eligible for blood donation. More importantly, reduction to the three-month deferral period is working well for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italy and Spain have implemented behavioural-based screening approaches, which have been supported by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americasblood.org/media/27919/stmnt_060309_deferrals-msm.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;American Red Cross and American Association of Blood Banks&lt;/a&gt;, and screen all individuals (including gay men) into “low-risk” and “high-risk” groups based on their sexual behaviours. For example, individuals who are in long-term monogamous relationships, or practice regular safe sex, are unlikely to have contracted HIV that would be undetectable at the time of donation and are therefore labelled “low-risk”. On the other hand, individuals who have unprotected sex, or are engaged in anonymous sexual encounters, are more likely to have contracted HIV and are labelled “high-risk”. Currently, this approach is working in Italy and Spain and increases the number of eligible donors while preventing the further stigmatization of gay men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A behavioural-based approach is the ideal option for reducing the stigmatization of gay blood, as well as increasing the number of potential donors, while still protecting the blood supply from HIV contamination. Canadian advocates, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://bloodwatch.org/about/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;BloodWatch&lt;/a&gt;, support a decrease in the deferral period to three-months, but agree that a behavioural-based approach is preferable. Importantly, the diagnostic tests which currently screen for HIV are incredibly robust tools, and with proper donor screening and blood testing, Canadian Blood Services can ensure that supplies remain safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, as I have argued before, Canadian Blood Services needs to work quickly to implement better policy as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctvnews.ca/health/canadian-blood-services-seeking-22-000-donors-to-avoid-shortage-1.4051904&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;blood shortages continue to be a problem&lt;/a&gt;. It is my, and others, hope that this policy can change soon, and Canada can become a world-leader in blood donation policy for gay men. Gay blood ban policies are based in an outdated and unsupported fear of blood donation from gay men. Therefore, we must work faster to update our policies to ensure our blood donation policies so as to prevent stigmatization, as well as ensure that our blood supply remains safe, and our policies are backed by science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landongetz.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/a&gt; is a gay man and a Ph.D. Candidate in the Microbiology and Immunology Department at Dalhousie University &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;@landongetz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">Landon J. Getz provides an update on Canadian Blood Services’ progress in updating outmoded policies on gay blood donation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/10/red_blood_cell.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Privacy Implications of Human DNA Sequencing</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/privacy/sequencing/ethics/law%20&%20policy/2018/05/11/DNAPrivacyIssuesIE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Privacy Implications of Human DNA Sequencing" /><published>2018-05-11T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2018-05-11T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/privacy/sequencing/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/05/11/DNAPrivacyIssuesIE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/privacy/sequencing/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2018/05/11/DNAPrivacyIssuesIE/">&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;a href=&quot;www.impactethics.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Impact Ethics&lt;/a&gt; on May 11th, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/b&gt; explores the privacy minefield of commercial DNA Sequencing, and how it has become relevant in recent news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deoxyribonucleic acid, or DNA, has been known as the hereditary material in living cells since 1944. It was discovered, in part, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Oswald-Avery&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Halifax-born Oswald Avery&lt;/a&gt;. Since being discovered, scientists have made significant progress in figuring out how DNA is manufactured, copied, and used by living cells. Most importantly, in the last decade we have become &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/27541954/dna-sequencing-costs-data/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;remarkably good at “sequencing”&lt;/a&gt; the genetic code: decoding the DNA molecules so that we can read the genetic blueprint, much like one would translate a book from one language to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to sequence DNA has provided many opportunities for researchers and clinicians alike to understand the nature and likelihood of some hereditary diseases. It has also allowed us to identify persons who are genetically-related to one another. Databases, both public and private, are being built to collect and store this genetic data. Examples include private companies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.23andme.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;23andMe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ancestry.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;AncestryDNA&lt;/a&gt;, along with public databases like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gedmatch.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;GEDMatch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variety of privacy and intimate-information issues stem from obtaining and storing personal DNA sequence information. For example, AncestryDNA provides a genetic heritage analysis, allowing an individual to learn where their DNA tells them they are from. (It should be noted that the ability of these tests to identify heritage correctly has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/how-dna-testing-botched-my-familys-heritage-and-probab-1820932637&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;called into question&lt;/a&gt;). This information can be shared with others, dependent on the privacy selections an individual makes on their profile. It is essential that customers ensure their privacy settings are as they want them to be, to ensure their data stays private (if that’s what they wish).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/dna.jpg?w=640&amp;#038;h=615&quot; alt=&quot;Playing with Code Fire; by Ade McOran-Campbell (2011). Image description: Painting of person sitting cross-legged in a field, with the sun overhead. Person is playing with a double helix.&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Playing with Code Fire; by Ade McOran-Campbell (2011). Image description: Painting of person sitting cross-legged in a field, with the sun overhead. Person is playing with a double helix.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, companies that collect genetic information to determine health risks – if you are a cystic fibrosis carrier for example – can learn things about themselves that they may otherwise wish not to know, or would want to keep out of the hands of others (e.g. insurance companies). Most strikingly, you not only learn your own health risks, but inadvertently you learn about your parents’ and relatives’ genetic codes as well. Your genetic code is hereditary after-all, meaning you receive your genes (and their associated health-risks) from your parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, a suspect in a string of sexual assaults and murders in the United States was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/04/golden-state-killer-east-area-rapist-dna-genealogy/559070/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;identified by police through a DNA sequence match&lt;/a&gt; on GEDMatch.com. GEDMatch works by allowing individuals to upload their personal genetic information to the database, in the hopes of identifying genealogical information. Police, undoubtedly through a genetic genealogist, used DNA samples collected at the crime scene to link the suspect to a family member who had uploaded their information to GEDMatch. This provided the police with the information they needed to make an arrest. This example highlights an additional use of publicly available genetic information that many people were unaware of. This particular example is worrying. Although the end in this case – catching and subduing a suspected serial killer and rapist – was undeniably good, the family member who uploaded their DNA sequence to GEDMatch was likely unaware of how it would be used. This ultimately puts the family member in the position of “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/04/20/AR2008042002388.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;genetic informant&lt;/a&gt;” without their knowledge. As such, this particular case has raised many questions about how police should be able to use genealogy websites and their associated data. Further issues are raised by the fact that the use of DNA sequences in this way is not always accurate. DNA evidence was used to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theadvocate.com/new_orleans/news/article_1b3a3f96-d574-59e0-9c6a-c3c7c0d2f166.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;link a San Francisco film-maker to a murder&lt;/a&gt; that police later found out he did not commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2017/03/canada-s-new-genetic-privacy-law-causing-huge-headaches-justin-trudeau&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Canadian law currently prevents the use of genetic information to discriminate&lt;/a&gt; for housing, employment and insurance, with significant criminal consequences if that law is violated. Canadians, however, are only covered by this law while in Canada. This does not prevent genetic information from being used for a variety of other things by private companies in other countries. David Fraser, a Halifax privacy lawyer, issued a warning in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/dna-testing-privacy-terms-and-conditions-1.4508488&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;2018 CBC interview&lt;/a&gt; that “this is some of the most sensitive information that exists,” and that not everyone considers the implications of DNA testing. In writing this, I wished to echo that statement: DNA testing provides a wealth of information that can be used in a variety of ways, both good and bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important that consumers are aware of what they are getting into and what the private companies will do with their information once the DNA sequencing is complete. Ultimately, understanding these details allows consumers to make informed decisions about this extremely personal information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landongetz.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/a&gt; is a M.Sc. Candidate with the Department of Microbiology and Immunology at Dalhousie University. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;@landongetz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">Landon J. Getz explores the privacy minefield of commercial DNA Sequencing, and how it has become relevant in recent news.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/dna.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://impactethics.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/dna.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A Reflection on Blood Donation Policy in Canada</title><link href="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&%20policy/2017/08/24/ReflectionBloodPolicyIE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Reflection on Blood Donation Policy in Canada" /><published>2017-08-24T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2017-08-24T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2017/08/24/ReflectionBloodPolicyIE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://landongetz.github.io//blog/blood%20ban/lgbtq+/ethics/law%20&amp;%20policy/2017/08/24/ReflectionBloodPolicyIE/">&lt;p&gt;Published on &lt;a href=&quot;www.impactethics.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Impact Ethics&lt;/a&gt; on August 24th, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/b&gt; reflects on the current sexual abstention period within Canada for blood donations by men who have sex with men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving through Halifax during pride week, I noticed a Pride advertisement on the back of a city bus. It noted a headline from a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/gay-men-blood-donations-1.3643761&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Global News article&lt;/a&gt; titled: &lt;em&gt;Canada’s limitations on gay blood donations ‘ridiculous’: HIV researchers&lt;/em&gt;. Currently, in Canada, men who have sex with men are prohibited from donating blood if they have had sex with a man in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blood.ca/en/men-who-have-sex-men&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;year prior&lt;/a&gt; to their donation. Even though many LGBTQ advocates and HIV researchers are saying this deferral period on blood donation by men who have had sex with men is ‘ridiculous,’ Canadian Blood Services and Health Canada do not seem to agree. Approximately one year ago, the current 1-year deferral period policy replaced a 5-year deferral period. The anniversary of this policy change marks an opportunity to reflect on Canada’s blood donation policy and what it means for the LGBTQ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, bans, deferral periods, and restrictions on blood donation by gay/bisexual men have been rooted in fear of harming patients by exposing them to contaminated blood. HIV was discovered in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theaidsinstitute.org/node/259&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;1983&lt;/a&gt;, and from there new methods of diagnosis were discovered. Unfortunately, this did not stop HIV-infected blood from entering the blood supply, leading to what is known today as the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/strombo/news/canadas-tainted-blood-scandal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Tainted Blood Scandal&lt;/a&gt;.” Consequently, roughly 2000 Canadians were exposed to HIV via blood products in the early 1980s. However, a lack of policy and proper diagnostic testing procedures played important roles in this problem. While previously, diagnostic tests took months to diagnose HIV, modern tests can identify the virus in blood two weeks after exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure  figure--center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;image&quot; src=&quot;https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/HPIEpost.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image Description: Halifax Pride Advertisement 2017.&quot; width=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Image Description: Halifax Pride Advertisement 2017.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This two-week window gets right at the root of why a 1-year deferral period for gay/bisexual men is no longer necessary from an infectious diseases perspective. Selecting this duration seems arbitrary when we have confidence that we can detect HIV infection within two weeks. So, the question here is why Canadian Blood Services continue to impose lengthy donation restrictions for men in this group when the risk of HIV contaminated blood entering the blood supply exists only for two weeks after sexual contact. Canadian Blood Services states that their &lt;a href=&quot;https://blood.ca/en/msm/about-men-who-have-sex-with-men&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;reason&lt;/a&gt; for maintaining the 1-year deferral period is that gay/bisexual men make up the largest proportion of individuals newly infected with HIV. However, sexual behaviours among gay/bisexual men vary greatly, and certain behaviours can significantly reduce an individual’s risk of exposure to HIV. Examples include having protected sex (using condoms), being in a monogamous relationship where both partners are HIV negative, and avoiding sexual encounters with anonymous individuals. While the statistics tell us that gay/bisexual men are the most likely to become infected with HIV, it does not mean that &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; men who have sex with men are at a high risk for HIV exposure. As well, Canadian Blood Services &lt;a href=&quot;https://blood.ca/en/blood/blood-safety&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;tests all donated blood&lt;/a&gt; samples via modern diagnostic tests for infectious disease contamination. If contamination does occur, the screening process prevents it from entering the blood supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an organization whose slogans focus on how we can each give life, it is worrisome that a portion of the population is restricted from doing so by policy that, at best, seems no longer necessary. Especially considering the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/critical-blood-shortage-1.4164669&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;current blood shortage issues&lt;/a&gt; in Canada, we need to ensure that any prohibition on donation is for reasons that are worthy. The current policy seems to fail here because diagnostic testing has improved, such that HIV can be detected in the blood within two weeks of infection. Also, the risk of contaminating the blood supply with HIV can be reduced by screening for certain sexual behaviours, rather than simply screening on the basis of sexual orientation.
    
Replacement of the 1-year deferral period is necessary because gay/bisexual men are interested in donating blood and not all are at increased risk for HIV infection. Further, gay/bisexual men are already stigmatized and policy that does not accurately reflect risks acts to further this stigma. The facts tell us a shorter abstention period from risky sexual practices would be sufficiently long to ensure a safe blood supply. Even further, for individuals who are taking appropriate precautions when it comes to protected sex, or who have been in long-term, HIV-negative, monogamous relationships, it hardly seems appropriate to have a deferral period at all. For a future of blood donation that is more based on facts, Canadian Blood Services must understand that current policy is not a worthwhile solution to infection control. As well, future statistics collected on HIV infections should be focused on sexual practices and behaviours rather than simply on sexual orientation. Finally, blood donation for men who have sex with men is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/news/health/gay-blood-donation-sex-aids-three-months-year-a7721606.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;already changing&lt;/a&gt; in places around the world. Canada's blood donation policy has changed before, and it is time for it to change again.


&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://landongetz.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Landon J. Getz&lt;/a&gt; is a gay man and an MSc Candidate with Dalhousie University’s Department of Microbiology and Immunology. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LandonGetz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;@landongetz&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>LandonGetz</name></author><summary type="html">Landon J. Getz reflects on the current sexual abstention period within Canada for blood donations by men who have sex with men.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/HPIEpost.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://landongetz.github.io/blog/images/HPIEpost.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>